In the previous video, we preprocessed our data,
and we're now ready to extract the word frequencies to be
used in our prediction problem.
The tm package provides a function called
DocumentTermMatrix that generates a matrix where
the rows correspond to documents, in our case tweets,
and the columns correspond to words in those tweets.
The values in the matrix are the number
of times that word appears in each document.
Let's go ahead and generate this matrix
and call it "frequencies."
So we'll use the DocumentTermMatrix function
calls on our corpus that we created in the previous video.
Let's take a look at our matrix by typing frequencies.
We can see that there are 3,289 terms
or words in our matrix and 1,181 documents
or tweets after preprocessing.
Let's see what this matrix looks like using
the inspect function.
So type  inspect(frequencies[1000:1005, 505:515]).
In this range we see that the word "cheer" appears
in the tweet 1005, but "cheap" doesn't
appear in any of these tweets.
This data is what we call sparse.
This means that there are many zeros in our matrix.
We can look at what the most popular terms are,
or words, with the function findFreqTerms.
We want to call this on our matrix frequencies,
and then we want to give an argument lowFreq, which
is equal to the minimum number of times
a term must appear to be displayed.
Let's type 20.
We see here 56 different words.
So out of the 3,289 words in our matrix,
only 56 words appear at least 20 times in our tweets.
This means that we probably have a lot of terms
that will be pretty useless for our prediction model.
The number of terms is an issue for two main reasons.
One is computational.
More terms means more independent variables,
which usually means it takes longer to build our models.
The other is in building models, as we mentioned
before, the ratio of independent variables to observations
will affect how good the model will generalize.
So let's remove some terms that don't appear very often.
We'll call the output sparse, and we'll use
the removeSparseTerms(frequencies,
0.98).
The sparsity threshold works as follows.
If we say 0.98, this means to only keep
terms that appear in 2% or more of the tweets.
If we say 0.99, that means to only keep
terms that appear in 1% or more of the tweets.
If we say 0.995, that means to only keep
terms that appear in 0.5% or more of the tweets,
about six or more tweets.
We'll go ahead and use this sparsity threshold.
If you type sparse, you can see that there's
only 309 terms in our sparse matrix.
This is only about 9% of the previous count of 3,289.
Now let's convert the sparse matrix into a data frame
that we'll be able to use for our predictive models.
We'll call it tweetsSparse and use the as.data.frame function
called on the as.matrix function called on our matrix sparse.
This converts sparse to a data frame called tweetsSparse.
Since R struggles with variable names that start with a number,
and we probably have some words here that start with a number,
let's run the make.names function to make sure
all of our words are appropriate variable names.
To do this type colnames and then in parentheses the name
of our data frame, tweetsSparse equals
make.names(colnames(tweetsSparse)).
This will just convert our variable names
to make sure they're all appropriate names
before we build our predictive models.
You should do this each time you've
built a data frame using text analytics.
Now let's add our dependent variable to this data set.
We'll call it tweetsSparse$Negative
and set it equal to the original Negative variable from the tweets data frame.
Lastly, let's split our data into a training set
and a testing set, putting 70% of the data in the training
set.
First we'll have to load the library caTools so that we
can use the sample.split function.
Then let's set the seed to 123 and create our split using
sample.split where our dependent variable is
tweetsSparse$Negative.
And then our split ratio will be 0.7.
We'll put 70% of the data in the training set.
Then let's just use subset to create a treating set called
trainSparse, which will take a subset of the whole data set
tweetsSparse, but always take the observations for which
split is equal to TRUE.
And we'll create our test set, testSparse,
again using subset to take the observations of tweetsSparse,
but this time for which split is equal to FALSE.
Our data is now ready, and we can build our predictive model.
In the next video, we'll use CART and logistic regression
to predict negative sentiment.