The game of Jeopardy has three rounds.
Jeopardy, Double Jeopardy, where the dollar values are doubled,
and Final Jeopardy, when contestants
can wager an amount of money on one single question.
Each round has five questions in six categories.
It consists of a wide variety of topics,
over 2,500 different categories.
Each question has dollar value.
The first to buzz in and answer correctly wins the money.
If they answer incorrectly, they lose the money.
An example of a round involves the following categories:
Dinosaurs, Notable Women, Oxford English Dictionary,
Name That Instrument, Belgium, and Composers by Country.
The type of questions Jeopardy includes,
includes cryptic definitions of categories and clues.
And the answer is in the form of a question.
Let me give you two examples.
Question is: Mozart's last and perhaps most powerful symphony
shares its name with this planet.
The answer should be, "What is Jupiter?"
Another example: smaller than only Greenland,
it's the world's second largest island.
And the answer, "What is New Guinea?"
Welcome back.
Ken, you've got your signalling device ready I see.
Here are the categories for you to select
from in Double Jeopardy.
First off, Etude, Brute.
Next, Hedgehog-Podge.
Don't Worry About It.
The Art of the Steal.
Cambridge.
And finally, "Church" & "State" with each of those words
in quotation marks.
Start us off.
Let's try "Don't Worry About It",
all the down at $2,000, Alex.
It's just acne!
You don't have this skin infection also known
as Hansen's disease.
Watson.
What is leprosy?
You are right.
"Etude, Brute" for $1,600.
Music fans wax rhapsodic about this Hungarian's
"transcendental etudes."
Watson.
Who is Franz Liszt?
You are right.
"Don't Worry About It" for $1,600.
You're just a little stiff!
You don't have this painful mosquito-borne joint illness
with a Swahili name.
Watson.
What is Dengue Fever.
Dengue Fever, correct.
"Etude, Brute" for $1,200.
Paganini's "24 Capricci" set the standard for etudes
for this instrument.
Watson.
What is violin?
Good.