Now that we've trained a model, we
need to evaluate it on the test set.
So let's build an object called pred
that has the predicted probabilities
for each class from our CART model.
So we'll use predict of emailCART, our CART model,
passing it newdata=test, to get test set predicted
probabilities.
So to recall the structure of pred,
we can look at the first 10 rows with pred[1:10,].
So this is the rows we want.
We want all the columns.
So we'll just leave a comma and nothing else afterward.
So the left column here is the predicted probability
of the document being non-responsive.
And the right column is the predicted probability
of the document being responsive.
They sum to 1.
So in our case, we want to extract
the predicted probability of the document being responsive.
So we're looking for the rightmost column.
So we'll create an object called pred.prob.
And we'll select the rightmost or second column.
All right.
So pred.prob now contains our test set
predicted probabilities.
And we're interested in the accuracy
of our model on the test set.
So for this computation, we'll use a cutoff of 0.5.
And so we can just table the true outcome,
which is test$responsive against the predicted outcome,
which is pred.prob >= 0.5.
What we can see here is that in 195 cases,
we predict false when the left column and the true outcome
was zero, non-responsive.
So we were correct.
And in another 25, we correctly identified a responsive
document.
In 20 cases, we identified a document as responsive,
but it was actually non-responsive.
And in 17, the opposite happened.
We identified a document as non-responsive,
but it actually was responsive.
So our accuracy is 195 + 25, our correct results,
divided by the total number of elements
in the testing set, 195 + 25 + 17 + 20.
So we have an accuracy in the test set of 85.6%.
And now we want to compare ourselves
to the accuracy of the baseline model.
As we've already established, the baseline model
is always going to predict the document is non-responsive.
So if we table test$responsive, we see that it's going to be
correct in 215 of the cases.
So then the accuracy is 215 divided
by the total number of test set observations.
So that's 83.7% accuracy.
So we see just a small improvement
in accuracy using the CART model, which, as we know,
is a common case in unbalanced data sets.
However, as in most document retrieval applications,
there are uneven costs for different types of errors here.
Typically, a human will still have to manually review
all of the predicted responsive documents
to make sure they are actually responsive.
Therefore, if we have a false positive,
in which a non-responsive document is labeled
as responsive, the mistake translates
to a bit of additional work in the manual review
process but no further harm, since the manual review process
will remove this erroneous result.
But on the other hand, if we have a false negative,
in which a responsive document is labeled as non-responsive
by our model, we will miss the document entirely
in our predictive coding process.
Therefore, we're going to assign a higher cost to false negatives
than to false positives, which makes this a good time to look
at other cut-offs on our ROC curve.