Now let's build the document-term matrix
for our corpus.
So we'll create a variable called
dtm that contains the DocumentTermMatrix(corpus).
The corpus has already had all the pre-processing run on it.
So to get the summary statistics about the document-term matrix,
we'll just type in the name of our variable, dtm.
And what we can see is that even though we
have only 855 emails in the corpus,
we have over 22,000 terms that showed up at least once,
which is clearly too many variables
for the number of observations we have.
So we want to remove the terms that
don't appear too often in our data set,
and we'll do that using the removeSparseTerms function.
And we're going to have to determine the sparsity,
so we'll say that we'll remove any term that doesn't appear
in at least 3% of the documents.
To do that, we'll pass 0.97 to removeSparseTerms.
Now we can take a look at the summary statistics
for the document-term matrix, and we
can see that we've decreased the number of terms
to 788, which is a much more reasonable number.
So let's build a data frame called labeledTerms out
of this document-term matrix.
So to do this, we'll use as.data.frame
of as.matrix applied to dtm, the document-term matrix.
So this data frame is only including right now
the frequencies of the words that appeared in at least 3%
of the documents, but in order to run our text analytics
models, we're also going to have the outcome variable, which
is whether or not each email was responsive.
So we need to add in this outcome variable.
So we'll create labeledTerms$responsive,
and we'll simply copy over the responsive variable from
the original emails data frame so it's equal
to emails$responsive.
So finally let's take a look at our newly constructed data
frame with the str function.
So as we expect, there are an awful lot of variables, 789 in total.
788 of those variables are the frequencies
of various words in the emails, and the last one is responsive,
the outcome variable.