Now let's look at the ROC curve so we
can understand the performance of our model
at different cutoffs.
We'll first need to load the ROCR package
with a library(ROCR).
Next, we'll build our ROCR prediction object.
So we'll call this object predROCR =
prediction(pred.prob, test$responsive).
All right.
So now we want to plot the ROC curve
so we'll use the performance function to extract
the true positive rate and false positive rate.
So create something called perfROCR =
performance(predROCR, "tpr", "fpr").
And then we'll plot(perfROCR, colorize=TRUE),
so that we can see the colors for the different cutoff
thresholds.
All right.
Now, of course, the best cutoff to select
is entirely dependent on the costs assigned by the decision
maker to false positives and true positives.
However, again, we do favor cutoffs
that give us a high sensitivity.
We want to identify a large number of the responsive
documents.
So something that might look promising
might be a point right around here,
in this part of the curve, where we
have a true positive rate of around 70%,
meaning that we're getting about 70%
of all the responsive documents, and a false positive rate
of about 20%, meaning that we're making mistakes
and accidentally identifying as responsive 20%
of the non-responsive documents.
Now, since, typically, the vast majority of documents
are non-responsive, operating at this cutoff
would result, perhaps, in a large decrease
in the amount of manual effort needed
in the eDiscovery process.
And we can see from the blue color
of the plot at this particular location
that we're looking at a threshold around maybe 0.15
or so, significantly lower than 50%, which is definitely
what we would expect since we favor
false positives to false negatives.
So lastly, we can use the ROCR package
to compute our AUC value.
So, again, call the performance function
with our prediction object, this time extracting the AUC value
and just grabbing the y value slot of it.
We can see that we have an AUC in the test set of 79.4%, which
means that our model can differentiate
between a randomly selected responsive and non-responsive
document about 80% of the time.