Let's conclude with a word about the status of predictive coding
today.
In legal systems, it's difficult to change existing practice
because of laws reliance on past precedent, which
causes current decisions to be made on the basis of past ones.
Because the types of eDiscovery admissible in court
have historically been limited to keyword search coupled
with manual review, nearly all cases
today use this eDiscovery approach.
However, this status quo seems to be starting to change.
In 2012, a US District Court ruled that predictive coding
was a legitimate eDiscovery tool, which
may pave the way for its expanded use in coming years.