We were able to solve our sports scheduling problem
with four teams, 24 decision variables, and 22
basic constraints pretty quickly.
However, the problem size increases rapidly.
The same problem with 10 teams would
have 585 decision variables, and 175 basic constraints.
For scheduling Major League Baseball,
the problem has 100,000 decision variables,
and 200,000 constraints.
For small problems, spreadsheet softwares like LibreOffice
are great.
But for large problems like this,
solving them in LibreOffice would be impossible.
So how are integer optimization models like this
solved in practice?
Many different tricks are used to solve large integer
optimization problems.
One is to reformulate the problem.
The sports scheduling problem with more teams
is often solved by changing the formulation.
Instead of the decision variables
we discussed in this lecture, the variables
are sequences of games.
Additionally, the problem can be split into three smaller
problems that can each be solved separately and much faster
than just solving the whole problem.
Another trick that's often used is
what are called heuristic methods.
These methods find good, but not necessarily optimal, decisions.
A good decision is sometimes accepted,
since the problem is so much easier
to solve using a heuristic method.
In addition to changing the formulation
and using heuristics, there are general purpose optimization
solvers that can solve large problems.
These include CPLEX, Gurobi, GLPK,
and Cbc, a COIN-OR project.
Most practitioners who solve large optimization problems
use one of these software packages.
And in the past 20 years, the speed of integer optimization
solvers has increased by a factor of 250,000,
which doesn't even include the increasing speed of computers.
Assuming a modest machine speed-up of 1,000,
this means that a problem that can
be solved in one second today took seven years
to solve 20 years ago.
Because of this increase in speed,
we're able to solve much larger and more complicated
optimization problems today than just a few years ago.
So how about the sports scheduling problem?
When the Sports Scheduling Group was started in 1996,
integer optimization software was too slow to be useful.
Now, they can use powerful solvers
to generate sports schedules.
Even with these solvers, it can take
months to make the Major League Baseball schedule.
This is due to several reasons, including the enormous list
of ever-changing constraints that they
have to account for, the need to define priorities
on the constraints to find a feasible solution, and the fact
that it takes several iterations to get a good schedule.
But even with these challenges, analytics
offers a significant edge in sports scheduling.
The use of optimization allows for the addition
of new constraints or schedule changes.
A new schedule can easily be generated
based on an updated requirement or request.
Now all professional sports, and most college sports,
construct their schedules using optimization.
In this lecture, we've seen one powerful use
of integer optimization.
But this method has a huge number
of applications, which you'll see
more of in the second lecture, the recitation,
and in the homework assignment.