To predict the outcomes of the Supreme Court,
Martin used cases from 1994 through 2001.
He chose this period of time because the Supreme Court
was composed of the same nine justices that
were justices when he made his predictions in 2002.
These nine justices were Breyer, Ginsburg, Kennedy, O'Connor,
Rehnquist-- who was the Chief Justice-- Scalia, Souter,
Stevens, and Thomas.
This was a very rare data set, since as I mentioned earlier,
this was the longest period of time
with the same set of justices in over 180 years.
This allowed Martin to use a larger data set
then might have been available if he
was doing this experiment at a different time.
In this lecture, we'll focus on predicting
Justice Stevens' decisions.
He is generally considered a justice
who started out moderate, but became
more liberal during his time on the Supreme Court--
although, he's a self-proclaimed conservative.
In this problem, our dependent variable
is whether or not Justice Stevens
voted to reverse the lower court decision.
This is a binary variable taking value 1 if Justice Stevens
decided to reverse or overturn the lower court decision,
and taking value 0 if Justice Stevens voted
to affirm or maintain the lower court decision.
Our independent variables are six different properties
of the case.
The circuit court of origin is the circuit
or lower court where the case came from.
There are 13 different circuit courts in the United States.
The 1st through 11th and Washington,
DC courts are defined by region.
And the federal court is defined by the subject
matter of the case.
The issue area of the case gives each case
a category, like civil rights or federal taxation.
The type of petitioner and type of respondent
define two parties in the case.
Some examples are the United States, an employer,
or an employee.
The ideological direction of the lower court decision
describes whether the lower court
made what was considered a liberal
or a conservative decision.
The last variable indicates whether or not
the petitioner argued that a law or practice was
unconstitutional.
To collect this data, Martin and his colleagues
read through all of the cases and coded the information.
Some of it, like the circuit court, is straightforward.
But other information required a judgment call,
like the ideological direction of the lower court.
Now that we have our data and variables,
we are ready to predict the decisions of Justice Stevens.
We can use logistic regression,
and we get a model where some of the most significant variables
are: whether or not the case is from the 2nd circuit court,
with a coefficient of 1.66;
whether or not the case is from the 4th circuit court,
with a coefficient of 2.82;
and whether or not the lower court decision
was liberal, with a coefficient of negative 1.22.
While this tells us that the case being
from the 2nd or 4th circuit courts
is predictive of Justice Stevens reversing the case,
and the lower court decision being liberal
is predictive of Justice Stevens affirming the case,
it's difficult to understand which factors
are more important due to things like the scales
of the variables, and the possibility
of multicollinearity.
It's also difficult to quickly evaluate
what the prediction would be for a new case.
So instead of logistic regression,
Martin and his colleagues used a method
called classification and regression trees, or CART.
This method builds what is called a tree
by splitting on the values of the independent variables.
To predict the outcome for a new observation or case,
you can follow the splits in the tree and at the end,
you predict the most frequent outcome
in the training set that followed the same path.
Some advantages of CART are that it does not
assume a linear model, like logistic regression
or linear regression, and it's a very interpretable model.
Let's look at an example.
This plot shows sample data for two independent variables, x
and y, and each data point is colored
by the outcome variable, red or gray.
CART tries to split this data into subsets
so that each subset is as pure or homogeneous as possible.
The first three splits that CART would create are shown here.
Then the standard prediction made by a CART model
is just the majority in each subset.
If a new observation fell into one of these two subsets, then
we would predict red, since the majority
of the observations in those subsets are red.
However, if a new observation fell
into one of these two subsets, we
would predict gray, since the majority of the observations
in those two subsets are gray.
A CART model is represented by what we call a tree.
The tree for the splits we just generated
is shown on the right.
The first split tests whether the variable x is less than 60.
If yes, the model says to predict red, and if no,
the model moves on to the next split.
Then, the second split checks whether or not
the variable y is less than 20.
If no, the model says to predict gray,
but if yes, the model moves on to the next split.
The third split checks whether or not
the variable x is less than 85.
If yes, then the model says to predict red, and if no,
the model says to predict gray.
There are a couple things to keep
in mind when reading trees.
In this tree, and for the trees we'll generate in R,
a yes response is always to the left and a no response
is always to the right.
Also, make sure you always start at the top of the tree.
The x less than 85 split only counts
for observations for which x is greater than 60
and y is less than 20.
In the next video, we'll discuss how
CART decides how many splits to generate
and how the final predictions are made.