In this video, we'll build a CART model
to predict healthcare cost.
First, let's make sure the packages rpart and rpart.plot
are loaded with the library function.
You should have already installed them
in the previous lecture on predicting Supreme Court
decisions.
Now, let's build our CART model.
We'll call it ClaimsTree.
And we'll use the rpart function to predict bucket2009,
using as independent variables: age, arthritis, alzheimers,
cancer, copd, depression, diabetes, heart.failure, ihd,
kidney, osteoporosis, and stroke.
We'll also use bucket2008 and reimbursement2008.
The data set we'll use to build our model is ClaimsTrain.
And then we'll add the arguments, method = "class",
since we have a classification problem here, and cp = 0.00005.
Note that even though we have a multi-class classification
problem here, we build our tree in the same way
as a binary classification problem.
So go ahead and hit Enter.
The cp value we're using here was
selected through cross-validation
on the training set.
We won't perform the cross-validation here,
because it takes a significant amount of time
on a data set of this size.
Remember that we have almost 275,000 observations
in our training set.
But keep in mind that the R commands
needed for cross-validation here are the same as those used
in the previous lecture on predicting Supreme Court
decisions.
So now that our model's done, let's
take a look at our tree with the prp function.
It might take a while to load, because we
have a huge tree here.
This makes sense for a few reasons.
One is the large number of observations in our training
set.
Another is that we have a five-class classification
problem, so the classification is
more complex than a binary classification case,
like the one we saw in the previous lecture.
The trees used by D2Hawkeye were also very large CART trees.
While this hurts the interpretability of the model,
it's still possible to describe each of the buckets of the tree
according to the splits.
So now, let's make predictions on the test set.
So go back to your R console, and we'll call our predictions
PredictTest, where we'll use the predict function for our model
ClaimsTree, and our newdata is ClaimsTest.
And we want to add type = "class"
to get class predictions.
And we can make our classification matrix
on the test set to compute the accuracy.
So we'll use the table function, where the actual outcomes are
ClaimsTest$bucket2009, and our predictions are PredictTest.
So to compute the accuracy, we need
to add up the numbers on the diagonal
and divide by the total number of observations in our test
set.
So we have 114141 + 16102 + 118 + 201 + 0.
And we'll divide by the number of rows in ClaimsTest.
So the accuracy of our model is 0.713.
For the penalty error, we can use our penalty matrix
like we did in the previous video.
So scroll up to the classification matrix command
and surround the table function by the as.matrix function,
and then we'll multiply by PenaltyMatrix.
So remember that this takes each entry in our classification
matrix and multiplies it by the corresponding number
in the penalty matrix.
So now we just need to add up all
of the numbers in this matrix by surrounding it by the sum
function and then dividing by the total number
of observations in our test set, or nrow(ClaimsTest).
So our penalty error is 0.758.
In the previous video, we saw that our baseline method
had an accuracy of 68% and a penalty error of 0.74.
So while we increased the accuracy,
the penalty error also went up.
Why?
By default, rpart will try to maximize the overall accuracy,
and every type of error is seen as having a penalty of one.
Our CART model predicts 3, 4, and 5 so rarely
because there are very few observations in these classes.
So we don't really expect this model
to do better on the penalty error than the baseline method.
So how can we fix this?
The rpart function allows us to specify
a parameter called loss.
This is the penalty matrix we want
to use when building our model.
So let's scroll back up to where we built our CART model.
At the end of the rpart function,
we'll add the argument parms = list(loss=PenaltyMatrix).
This is the name of the penalty matrix we created.
Close the parentheses and hit Enter.
So while our model is being built,
let's think about what we expect to happen.
If the rpart function knows that we'll
be giving a higher penalty to some types of errors
over others, it might choose different splits
when building the model to minimize
the worst types of errors.
We'll probably get a lower overall accuracy
with this new model.
But hopefully, the penalty error will be much lower too.
So now that our model is done, let's regenerate our test
set predictions by scrolling up to where we created PredictTest
and hitting Enter, and then recreating our classification
matrix by scrolling up to the table function
and hitting Enter again.
Now let's add up the numbers on the diagonal, 94310 + 18942
+ 4692 + 636 + 2, and divide by the number of rows
in ClaimsTest.
And hit Enter.
So the accuracy of this model is 0.647.
And we can scroll up and compute the penalty error here
by going back to the sum command and hitting Enter.
So the penalty error of our new model is 0.642.
Our accuracy is now lower than the baseline method,
but our penalty error is also much lower.
Note that we have significantly fewer independent variables
than D2Hawkeye had.
If we had the hundreds of codes and risk factors
available to D2Hawkeye, we would hopefully do even better.
In the next video, we'll discuss the accuracy of the models
used by D2Hawkeye and how analytics can provide an edge.