In real estate, there is a famous saying
that the most important thing is location, location, location.
In this recitation, we will be looking at regression trees,
and applying them to data related
to house prices and locations.
Boston is the capital of the state of Massachusetts, USA.
It was first settled in 1630, and in the greater Boston area
there are about 5 million people.
The area features some of the highest population
densities in America.
Here is a shot of Boston from above.
In the middle of the picture, we have the Charles River.
I'm talking to you from my office at MIT.
My office is here.
This is MIT here.
MIT lies in the city of Cambridge,
which is north of the river, and south of the river
is Boston city, itself.
In this recitation, we will be talking about Boston
in a sense of the greater Boston area.
However, if we look at the housing in Boston right now,
we can see that it is very dense.
Over the greater Boston area, the nature of the housing
varies widely.
This data comes from a paper, "Hedonic Housing Prices
and the Demand for Clean Air," which
has been cited more than 1,000 times.
This paper was written on a relationship between house
prices and clean air in the late 1970s
by David Harrison of Harvard and Daniel Rubinfeld
of the University of Michigan.
The data set is widely used to evaluate algorithms
of a nature we discuss in this class.
Now, in the lecture, we mostly
discuss classification trees with the output
as a factor or a category.
Trees can also be used for regression tasks.
The output at each leaf of a tree
is no longer a category, but a number.
Just like classification trees, regression trees can capture
nonlinearities that linear regression can't.
So what does that mean?
Well, with classification trees we report the average outcome
at each leaf of our tree.
For example, if the outcome is true 15 times,
and false 5 times, the value at that leaf of a tree would be
15/(15+5)=0.75.
Now, if we use the default threshold of 0.5,
we would say the value at this leaf is true.
With regression trees, we now have continuous variables.
So instead of-- we report the average
of the values at that leaf.
So suppose we had the values 3, 4, and 5
at one of the leaves of our trees.
Well, we just take the average of these numbers, which is 4,
and that is what we report.
That might be a bit confusing so let's look at a picture.
Here is some fake data that I made up in R.
We see x on the x-axis and y on the y-axis.
y is our variable we are trying to predict using x.
So if we fit a linear regression to this data set,
we obtain the following line.
As you can see, linear regression
does not do very well on this data set.
However, we can notice that the data
lies in three different groups.
If we draw these lines here, we see x is either less than 10,
between 10 and 20, or greater then 20,
and there is very different behavior in each group.
Regression trees can fit that kind of thing exactly.
So the splits would be x is less than or equal to 10,
take the average of those values.
x is between 10 and 20, take the average of those values.
x is between 20 and 30, take the average of those values.
We see that regression trees can fit some kinds of data
very well that linear regression completely fails on.
Of course, in reality nothing is ever so nice and simple,
but it gives us some idea why we might
be interested in regression trees.
So in this recitation, we will explore
the data set with the aid of trees.
We will compare linear regression
with regression trees.
We will discuss what the cp parameter means that we brought
up when we did cross-validation in the lecture,
and we will apply cross-validation
to regression trees.