We next discuss interventions suggested
by the model developed for the Framingham Heart Study.
The first intervention has to do with drugs
to lower blood pressure.
In FDR's time, hypertension drugs
were too toxic for practical use.
But in the 1950s, the diuretic chlorothiazide was developed,
and the Framingham Heart Study gave Ed Freis
the evidence needed to argue for testing effects for blood
pressure drugs.
In fact, the Veterans Administration Trial
was conducted.
This was a randomized, double blind clinical trial,
that found decreased risk of coronary heart disease.
Now, the market for diuretics worldwide
is more than a billion dollars.
Another intervention had to do with-- to lower cholesterol.
Despite the Framingham results, early cholesterol drugs
were too toxic for practical use.
But in the 1970s, the first statins were developed.
The study of 4,444 patients with CHD
revealed that statins cause a 37% risk
reduction of a second heart attack.
Furthermore, a study of 6,595 men with high cholesterol
revealed that statins cause a 32% risk reduction in deaths.
Now, the market for statins worldwide
is more than $20 billion.