Radiation therapy is one of the most well used applications
of optimization in health care.
In practice, radiation machines are
connected to treatment planning software that
implements and solves optimization
models, both linear optimization models, like we saw here,
and other types of optimization models.
Some examples of radiation machines
that use optimization software are Pinnacle by Philips,
RayStation by RaySearch Labs, and Eclipse by Varian.
There are many extensions to the optimization model
we described here.
One is the selection of beam angles.
The beam angles can be selected jointly with the intensity
profiles by using integer optimization.
This allows the treatment to be further personalized
to the specific tumor and person receiving the radiation.
Integer optimization is another type of optimization model
and will be the topic of next week.
Another extension is accounting for uncertainty.
Often, the quality of IMRT treatments
is degraded due to uncertain organ motion.
For example, in lung cancer the target area
is around the lungs.
But since the patient is breathing
throughout the treatment, the target area is moving
and the location is slightly uncertain.
We can manage this uncertainty using
a method known as robust optimization.
There is a significant amount of literature on this method
and its application to radiation therapy.
Linear optimization significantly
improves the efficiency of radiation therapy.
Manually designing an IMRT treatment
would be inefficient and impractical.
By using linear optimization, IMRT
can be designed in an efficient and systematic way.
As we saw in this lecture, clinical criteria
can be modeled using constraints,
and the treatment planner can explore trade-offs
by changing the model.
But ultimately, IMRT and the use of optimization
benefits the patient.
In head and neck cancers, saliva glands
were rarely spared prior to IMRT.
But by using optimized IMRT treatments,
saliva glands can now be spared.
In prostate cancer, IMRT treatments
reduce toxicities and allow for higher tumor doses
to be delivered safely.
And in lung cancer, optimized IMRT
reduced the risk of radiation induced pneumonitis.
These are just three examples of the benefits of IMRT.
Overall, optimized IMRT allows clinicians
to deliver treatment that was previously impossible
and to improve the quality of life for patients.