Let us try to understand the format of the data handed
to us in the CSV files.
Grayscale images are represented as a matrix of pixel intensity
values that range from zero to one.
The intensity value zero corresponds to the absence
of color, or black, and the value one corresponds to white.
For 8 bits per pixel images, we have 256 color levels
ranging from zero to one.
For instance, if we have the following grayscale image,
the pixel information can be translated
to a matrix of values between zero and one.
It is exactly this matrix that we are given in our datasets.
In other words, the datasets contain a table
of values between zero and one.
And the number of columns corresponds
to the width of the image, whereas the number of rows
corresponds to the height of the image.
In this example, the resolution is 7 by 7 pixels.
We have to be careful when reading the dataset in R.
We need to make sure that R reads
in the matrix appropriately.
Until now in this class, our datasets
were structured in a way where the rows refer to observations
and the columns refer to variables.
But this is not the case for the intensity matrix.
So keep in mind that we need to do some maneuvering
to make sure that R recognizes the data as a matrix.
Grayscale image segmentation can be done by clustering pixels
according to their intensity values.
So we can think of our clustering algorithm
as trying to divide the spectrum of intensity values
from zero to one into intervals, or clusters.
For instance, the red cluster corresponds
to the darkest shades, and the green cluster to the lightest.
Now, what should the input be to the clustering algorithm?
Well, our observations should be all of the 7
by 7 intensity values.
Hence, we should have 49 observations.
And we only have one variable, which
is the pixel intensity value.
So in other words, the input to the clustering algorithm
should be a vector containing 49 elements, or intensity values.
But what we have is a 7 by 7 matrix.
A crucial step before feeding the intensity
values to the clustering algorithm is morphing our data.
We should modify the matrix structure
and lump all the intensity values into a single vector.
We will see that we can do this in R
using the as.vector function.
Now, once we have the vector, we can simply
feed it into the clustering algorithm
and assign each element in the vector to a cluster.
Let us first use hierarchical clustering
since we are familiar with it.
The first step is to calculate the distance matrix, which
computes the pairwise distances among the elements
of the intensity vector.
How many such distances do we need to calculate?
Well, for each element in the intensity vector,
we need to calculate its distance from the other 48
elements.
So this makes 48 calculations per element.
And we have 49 such elements in the intensity vector.
In total, we should compute 49 times 48 pairwise distances.
But due to symmetry, we really need to calculate half of them.
So the number of pairwise distance calculations is
actually (49*48)/2.
In general, if we call the size of the intensity vector n,
then we need to compute n*(n-1)/2 pairwise distances
and store them in the distance matrix.
Now we should be ready to go to R.
I already navigated to the directory
where we saved the flower.csv file, which
contains the matrix of pixel intensities of a flower image.
Let us read in the matrix and save it to a data frame
and call it flower, then use the read.csv function
to instruct R to read in the flower dataset.
And then we have to explicitly mention
that we have no headers in the CSV file
because it only contains a matrix of intensity values.
So we're going to type header=FALSE.
Note that the default in R assumes
that the first row in the dataset is the header.
So if we didn't specify that we have no headers in this case,
we would have lost the information
from the first row of the pixel intensity matrix.
Now let us look at the structure of the flower data frame.
We realize that the way the data is stored
does not reflect that this is a matrix of intensity values.
Actually, R treats the rows as observations and the columns
as variables.
Let's try to change the data type to a matrix
by using the as.matrix function.
So let's define our variable flowerMatrix
and then use the as.matrix function, which
takes as an input the flower data frame.
And now if we look at the structure of the flower matrix,
we realize that we have 50 rows and 50 columns.
What this suggests is that the resolution of the image
is 50 pixels in width and 50 pixels in height.
This is actually a very, very small picture.
I am very curious to see how this image looks like, but lets
hold off now and do our clustering first.
We do not want to be influenced by how the image looks
like in our decision of the numbers of clusters
we want to pick.
To perform any type of clustering,
we saw earlier that we would need
to convert the matrix of pixel intensities
to a vector that contains all the intensity values ranging
from zero to one.
And the clustering algorithm divides the intensity spectrum,
the interval zero to one, into these joint clusters
or intervals.
So let us define the vector flowerVector,
and then now we're going to use the function as.vector, which
takes as an input the flowerMatrix.
And now if we look at the structure of the flowerVector,
we realize that we have 2,500 numerical values, which
range between zero and one.
And this totally makes sense because this reflects the 50
times 50 intensity values that we had in our matrix.
Now you might be wondering why we can't immediately
convert the data frame flower to a vector.
Let's try to do this.
So let's go back to our as.vector function
and then have the input be the flower data
frame instead of the flower matrix.
And then, let's name this variable flowerVector2, simply
so that we don't overwrite the flower vector.
And now let's look at its structure.
It seems that R reads it exactly like the flower data frame
and sees it as 50 observations and 50 variables.
So converting the data to a matrix and then to the vector
is a crucial step.
Now we should be ready to start our hierarchical clustering.
The first step is to create the distance matrix, as you already
know, which in this case computes
the difference between every two intensity values in our flower
vector.
So let's type distance=dist(flowerVector,
method="euclidean").
Now that we have the distance, next
we will be computing the hierarchical clusters.