What is the impact of clustering?
Clustering members within each cost bucket
yielded better predictions for heart attacks within clusters.
Grouping patients in clusters exhibits
temporal diagnostic patterns within nine months
of a heart attack.
These patterns can be incorporated
in the diagnostic rules for heart attacks.
The approach shows that using analytics for early heart
failure detection through pattern recognition
can lead to interesting new insights.
The findings here are reinforced by results from our research.
IBM, Sutter Health, and Geisinger Health Systems
partnered in 2009 to research analytics tools
in view of early detection.
Steve Steinhubl, a cardiologist from Geisinger,
wrote, "our early research showed
the signs and symptoms of heart failure in patients
are often documented years before diagnosis.
The pattern of documentation can offer clinically useful signals
for early detection of this deadly disease."