So how does clustering work?
The first step in clustering is to define
the distance between two data points.
The most popular way to compute the distance
is what's called Euclidean distance.
This is the standard way to compute distance
that you might have seen before.
Suppose we have two data points-- i
and j. The distance between the two points,
which we'll call dij, is equal to the square root
of the difference between the two
points in the first component, squared, plus the difference
between the two points in the second component,
squared, all the way up to the difference between the two
points in the k-th component, squared,
where k here is the number of attributes
or independent variables.
Let's see how this works by looking at an example.
In our movie lens dataset, we have binary vectors
for each movie, classifying that movie into genres.
The movie Toy Story is categorized
as an animation, comedy, and children's movie.
So the data for Toy Story has a 1
in the spot for these three genres and a 0 everywhere else.
The movie Batman Forever is categorized as an action,
adventure, comedy, and crime movie.
So Batman Forever has a 1 in the spot for these four genres
and a 0 everywhere else.
So given these two data observations,
let's compute the distance between them.
So the distance, d, would be equal to the square root
of (0-0)^2 + (0-1)^2 + (0-1)^2 + (1-0)^2 , etc.
This ends up being equal to the square root of 5.
In addition to Euclidean distance,
there are many other popular distance
metrics that could be used.
One is called Manhattan distance, where the distance is
computed to be the sum of the absolute values instead
of the sum of squares.
Another is called maximum coordinate distance,
where we only consider the measurement for which the data
points deviate the most.
Another important distance that we
have to calculate for clustering is the distance
between clusters, when a cluster is a group of data points.
We just discussed how to compute the distance between two
individual points, but how do we compute
the distance between groups of points?
One way of doing this is by using
what's called the minimum distance.
This defines the distance between clusters
as the distance between the two data points in the clusters
that are closest together.
For example, we would define the distance
between the yellow and red clusters
by computing the Euclidean distance between these two
points.
The other points in the clusters could be really far away,
but it doesn't matter if we use minimum distance.
The only thing we care about is how close together the closest
points are.
Alternatively, we could use maximum distance.
This one computes the distance between the two clusters
as the distance between the two points
that are the farthest apart.
So for example, we would compute the distance
between the yellow and red clusters
by looking at these two points.
Here, it doesn't matter how close together the other points
are.
All we care about is how close together the furthest points
The most common distance metric between clusters
is called centroid distance.
And this is what we'll use.
It defines the distance between clusters
by computing the centroid of the clusters.
The centroid is just the data point
that takes the average of all data points in each component.
This takes all data points in each cluster into account
and can be thought of as the middle data point.
In our example, the centroids between yellow and red
are here, and we would compute the distance
between the clusters by computing
the Euclidean distance between those two points.
When we are computing distances, it's
highly influenced by the scale of the variables.
As an example, suppose you're computing the distance
between two data points, where one variable is
the revenue of a company in thousands of dollars,
and another is the age of the company in years.
The revenue variable would really
dominate in the distance calculation.
The differences between the data points for revenue
would be in the thousands.
Whereas the differences between the year variable
would probably be less than 10.
To handle this, it's customary to normalize the data first.
We can normalize by subtracting the mean of the data
and dividing by the standard deviation.
We'll see more of this in the homework.
In our movie data set, all of our genre variables
are on the same scale.
So we don't have to worry about normalizing.
But if we wanted to add a variable, like box office
revenue, we would need to normalize
so that this variable didn't dominate all of the others.
Now that we've defined how we'll compute the distances,
we'll talk about a specific clustering algorithm--
hierarchical clustering-- in the next video.