In the previous video we identified clusters, or tissue
substances, in a healthy brain image.
It would be really helpful if we can
use these clusters to automatically detect
tumors in MRI images of sick patients.
The tumor.csv file corresponds to an MRI brain image
of a patient with oligodendroglioma,
a tumor that commonly occurs in the front lobe of the brain.
Since brain biopsy is the only definite diagnosis
of this tumor, MRI guidance is key in determining its location
and geometry.
Now, make sure that the tumor.csv file
is in your current directory.
Let's go to the console, and clear it, and then
read the data, and save it to a data frame
that we're going to call tumor, and use the read.csv function,
which takes as an input the tumor dataset,
and make sure to turn off the header using header
equals FALSE.
And let's quickly create our tumorMatrix,
using the as.matrix function over the tumor data
frame, and the tumorVector, using the as.vector
function over the tumorMatrix.
Now, we will not run the k-means algorithm again
on the tumor vector.
Instead, we will apply the k-means clustering results
that we found using the healthy brain
image on the tumor vector.
In other words, we treat the healthy vector
as training set and the tumor vector as a testing set.
To do this, we first need to install
a new package that is called flexclust.
So let us type install.packages("flexclust").
And then the first thing R will ask
us is to set the region that is closest
to our geographical location.
And after that, press OK, and the installation
shouldn't take more than two seconds to complete.
OK.
Now that the package is installed,
let us load it by typing library(flexclust).
The flexclust package contains the object class KCCA,
which stands for K-Centroids Cluster Analysis.
We need to convert the information from the clustering
algorithm to an object of the class KCCA.
And this conversion is needed before we
can use the predict function on the test set tumorVector.
So calling our new variable KMC.kcca
and then using the as.kcca function, which
takes as a first input the original KMC variable that
stored all the information from the k-means clustering
function, and the second input is the data that we clustered.
And in this case, it's the training set,
which is the healthyVector.
And now, be aware that this data conversion
will take some time to run.
Now that R finally finished creating the object KMC.kcca,
we can cluster the pixels in the tumorVector
using the predict function.
Let us call the cluster vector tumorClusters =
predict(KMC.kcca, newdata=tumorVector).
And now, the tumorClusters is a vector
that assigns a value 1 through 5 to each of the intensity
values in the tumorVector, as predicted
by the k-means algorithm.
To output the segmented image, we first
need to convert the tumor clusters to a matrix.
So let's use the dimension function,
and then the input is simply tumorClusters,
and then using the c function with the first input
as the number of rows in the tumorMatrix
and the second input as the number
of columns in the tumorMatrix.
And now, we can visualize the clusters
by using the image function with the input tumorClusters matrix,
and make sure to set the axes to FALSE,
and let's use again these fancy rainbow colors, here.
So col=rainbow(k).
Again, k is equal to 5.
Alright.
Let's navigate to the graphics window,
now, to see if we can detect the tumor.
Oh, and yes, we do!
It is this abnormal substance here
that is highlighted in blue that was not
present in the healthy MRI image.
So we were successfully able to identify, more or less,
the geometry of the malignant structure.
We see that we did a good job capturing the major tissue
substances of the brain.
The grey matter is highlighted in purple and the white matter
in yellow.
For the sick patient, the substance highlighted in blue
is the oligodendroglioma tumor.
Notice that we do not see substantial blue regions
in the healthy brain image, apart
from the region around the eyes.
Actually, looking at the eyes regions,
we notice that the two images were not taken precisely
at the same section of the brain.
This might explain some differences
in shapes between the two images.
Let's see how the images look like originally.
We see that the tumor region has a lighter color intensity,
which is very similar to the region around the eyes
in the healthy brain image.
This might explain highlighting this region in blue.
Of course, we cannot claim that we did a wonderful job
obtaining the exact geometries of all the tissue substances,
but we are definitely on the right track.
In fact, to do so, we need to use more advanced algorithms
and fine-tune our clustering technique.
MRI image segmentation is an ongoing field of research.
While k-means clustering is a good starting point,
more advanced techniques have been
proposed in the literature, such as the modified fuzzy k-means
clustering method.
Also, if you are interested, R has
packages that are specialized for analyzing medical images.
Now, if we had MRI axial images taken
at different sections of the brain,
we could segment each image and capture the geometries
of the substances at different levels.
Then, by interpolating between the segmented images,
we can estimate the missing slices,
and we can then obtain a 3D reconstruction
of the anatomy of the brain from 2D MRI cross-sections.
In fact, 3D reconstruction is particularly
important in the medical field for diagnosis,
surgical planning, and biological research purposes.
I hope that this recitation gave you
a flavor of this fascinating field of image segmentation.
In our next video, we will review all the analytics tools
we have covered so far in this class
and discuss their uses, pros, and cons.