So we just made this plot in ggplot2.
When we compare it back to the pie graph,
the first thing I notice is that now all the data is visible.
We haven't lost the small regions
and we can read out the exact share that
comes from Africa, Oceania, and the unknown or stateless
column.
I believe it is also easier to compare the relative sizes
of each region because they're all
put side by side on a similar scale.
There's no tricks, or three dimensions,
or colors to create a perception issue.
But, I will say that something to consider
is, for some people and some applications,
being not as visually exciting is a negative.
This plot, while very readable and correct,
is certainly a little bit dull.
In some applications, this is an important consideration.
Now, wouldn't it be interesting if we
could plot this data on a world map?
It would be possible, but a bit tedious
to create because we need to determine
which country lies in which region.
Shading all countries in a region of the same color
might be misleading though.
For example, countries in Latin America
will send students at different rates, naturally.
But, if we color them all the same color,
it kind of gives a false impression.
As it turns out, we actually have access
to per country data.
So we will plot that on a world map
instead and see if it is an effective way of communicating
where students come from to MIT.