The World Health Organization, WHO for short,
is the authority for health within the United Nations
system.
It is responsible for providing leadership on global health
matters, shaping the health research agenda,
setting norms and standards, articulating
evidence-based policy options, providing technical support
to countries, and monitoring and assessing health trends.
WHO communicates information about global health in order
to inform citizens, donors, policymakers, and organizations
around the world.
Their primary publication is World Health Report.
Each issue focuses on a specific aspect of global health,
and includes statistics and experts' assessments.
WHO also maintains an open, online repository
of global health data.
WHO provides some data visualizations,
which helps them communicate more
effectively with the public.
As an example, the graph shows the World Energy Consumption
during 2001 to 2003.